Guide to the Stanford University, President's Office, Records
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Stanford University, President's Office, records
1893-1960
SC0041
Stanford University. Office of the President
12 Linear feet
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Provenance
Administrative transfer, 1968-1975.
Information about Access
None.
SCOPE AND CONTENT
These records include letters from the President to the Board of Trustees, 1902-1948; budget records, 1906-1960; departmental appointment records, 1901-1909; salary rolls and letters of appointment, 1901-1924; contracts and agreements largely between Jane Stanford and David Starr Jordan, 1893-1902, regarding faculty salaries and university fees, budget matters, and the ground lease for University land; and reports of committee actions, 1898-1910. Presidents represented in these records are: David Starr Jordan (1891-1913), John Casper Branner (1913-1915), Ray Lyman Wilbur (1915-1943), and Donald B. Tresidder (1943-1948).
Access Terms
Branner, John Casper, 1850-1922.; Jordan, David Starr, 1851-1931; Stanford University. Board of Trustees.; Stanford, Jane Lathrop, 1828-1905.; Tresidder, Donald Bertrand, 1894-1948; Wilbur, Ray L., (Ray Lyman), 1875-1949
Collection Contents
- Letters to the Board of Trustees from the President, Series 1
  - Dec 28, 1908-Feb 15, 1910 (Box 1)
  - Feb 14, 1910-Mar 31, 1911 (Box 1)
  - Mar 2, 1911-Aug 1, 1912 (Box 1)
  - Aug 7, 1912-Jul 27, 1913 (Box 1)
  - Aug 14, 1913-Jul 28, 1914 (Box 1)
  - Aug 1, 1914-Jul 31, 1915 (Box 1)
  - Aug 1, 1915-Jul 31, 1916 (Box 1)
  - Aug 1, 1916-Jul 31, 1917 (Box 1)
  - Aug 1, 1917-Aug 31, 1918 (Box 1)
  - Sep 5, 1918-Aug 29, 1919 (Box 2)
  - Sep 4, 1919-Jul 31, 1920 (Box 2)
  - Aug 2, 1920-Aug 24, 1921 (Box 2)
  - Aug 25, 1921-Aug 1, 1922 (Box 2)
  - July 28, 1922 -July 31, 1923 (Box 2)
  - Aug 1, 1923-Jul 31, 1924 (Box 2)
  - Aug 1, 1924-Jul 30, 1925 (Box 2)
  - Aug 1, 1925-Aug 11, 1926 (Box 2)
  - Aug 17, 1926-Aug 11, 1927 (Box 3)
  - Aug 11, 1927-Aug 13, 1928 (Box 3)
  - Aug 17, 1928-Aug 14, 1929 (Box 3)
  - Aug 16, 1929-Aug 13, 1930 (Box 3)
  - Aug 15, 1930-Aug 12, 1931 (Box 3)
  - Aug 13, 1931-Sep 8, 1932 (Box 3)
  - Sep 10, 1932-Sep 14, 1933 (Box 4)
  - Sep 16, 1933-Aug 9, 1934 (Box 4)
  - Aug 10, 1934-Jul 17, 1935 (Box 4)
  - July 18, 1935 -May 30, 1936 (Box 4)
  - Jun 1, 1936-Mar 24, 1937 (Box 4)
  - Mar 24, 1937-Jan 18, 1938 (Box 4)
  - Jan 20, 1938-Oct 20, 1938 (Box 5)
  - Oct 20, 1938-Jul 19, 1939 (Box 5)
  - Jul 19, 1939-Mar 29, 1940 (Box 5)
  - Apr 1, 1940-Oct 16, 1940 (Box 5)
  - Oct 16, 1940-Apr 17, 1941 (Box 5)
  - Apr 18, 1941-Nov 26, 1941 (Box 5)
  - Nov 17, 1941-Jun 18, 1942 (Box 6)
  - Jun 19, 1942-Feb 26, 1943 (Box 6)
  - Feb 20, 1943-Jul 15, 1943 (Box 6)
  - Jul 13, 1943-Jan 19, 1944 (Box 6)
  - Jan 21, 1944-Jul 17, 1944 (Box 6)
    Beginning with this volume, the remaining volumes in Series 1 are indexed by subject.
  - July 17, 1944 -July 19, 1945 (Box 6)
  - July 19, 1945 -June 15, 1946 (Box 7)
  - May 28, 1946-Feb 15, 1947 (Box 7)
  - Feb 28, 1947-Sep 24, 1947 (Box 7)
  - Aug 8, 1947-May 14, 1948 (Box 7)
- Budget Data, Series 2
  - Submitted department budgets, Aug-Nov 1906 (Box 7)
  - Recommendations and appropriations, 1907-1908; 1908-1909 (Box 7)
  - Recommendations and appropriations, 1915-1916 (Box 7)
  - Recommendations and appropriations, 1916-1917 (Box 8)
  - Budget - President's copy, 1916-1917 (Box 8)
  - Budget - President's copy, 1918-1919 (Box 8)
  - Budget - President's copy, 1919-1920 (Box 8)
  - Budget - President's copy, 1920-1921 (Box 8)
  - Budget - President's copy, 1921-1922 (Box 8)
  - Budget - President's copy, 1922-1923 (Box 8)
  - Budget - President's copy, 1923-1924 (Box 9)
  - Budget - President's copy, 1924-1925 (Box 9)
  - Budget - President's copy, 1925-1926 (Box 9)
  - Budget - President's copy, 1926-1927 (Box 9)
  - Budget - President's copy, 1927-1928 (Box 9)
  - Budget - President's copy, 1928-1929 (Box 9)
  - Budget - President's copy, 1929-1930 (Box 10)
  - Budget - President's copy, 1930-1931 (Box 10)
  - Budget - President's copy, 1931-1932 (Box 10)
  - Budget - President's copy, 1932-1933 (Box 10)
  - Budget - President's copy, 1933-1934 (Box 10)
  - Budget - President's copy, 1934-1935 (Box 10)
  - Budget - President's copy, 1935-1936 (Box 10)
  - Budget - President's copy, 1936-1937 (Box 11)
  - Budget - President's copy, 1937-1938 (Box 11)
  - Budget - President's copy, 1938-1939 (Box 11)
  - Budget - President's copy, 1939-1940 (Box 11)
  - Budget - President's copy, 1940-1941 (Box 11)
  - Budget - President's copy, 1941-1942 (Box 11)
  - Budget - President's copy, 1942-1943 (Box 12)
  - Budget - President's copy (unbound), 1942-1943 (Box 12)
  - Budget - President's copy (unbound), 1942-1943 (Box 12)
  - Budget - President's copy, 1943-1944 (Box 12)
  - Budget - President's copy (unbound), 1943-1944 (Box 12)
  - Budget - President's copy, 1944-1945 (Box 12)
  - Budget - President's copy, 1944-1945 (Box 12)
  - Budget - President's copy, 1945-1946 (Box 12)
  - Budget - President's copy (unbound), 1945-1946 (Box 13)
  - Budget Book I, "bio" - "med" (unbound), 1946-1947 (Box 13)
  - Budget Book II, "min" - end (unbound), 1946-1947 (Box 13)
  - Budget Book I, "bio" - "med" (unbound), 1947-1948 (Box 13)
  - Budget Book II, "min" - end (unbound), 1947-1948 (Box 13)
  - Departmental Budget, 1948-1949 (Box 13)
  - Working Budget (unbound), 1948-1949 (Box 13)
  - Departmental Budget (unbound), 1949-1950 (Box 13)
  - Working Budget (unbound), 1949-1950 (Box 13)
  - Department Budget (unbound), 1950-1951 (Box 14)
  - Department Budget (unbound), 1951-1952 (Box 14)
  - Department Budget (unbound), 1951-1952 (Box 14)
  - Department Budget (unbound), 1952-1953 (Box 14)
  - Department Budget (unbound), 1952-1953 (Box 14)
  - Working budget (unbound), 1953-1954 (Box 14)
  - Working budget (unbound), 1954-1955 (Box 14)
  - Department Budget (unbound), 1955-1956 (Box 15)
  - Department Budget (unbound), 1956-1957 (Box 15)
  - Department Budget (unbound), 1957-1958 (Box 15)
  - Department Budget (unbound), 1958-1959 (Box 15)
  - Department Budget (unbound), 1959-1960 (Box 15)
- Departmental Appointments, Series 3
  - Regarding department needs and appointments, 1901-1904 (Box 15)
  - Assistants, 1905 (Box 15)
  - [Appointment], 1906 (Box 15)
  - Department Recommendations, 1907 (Box 15)
  - Department Appointment Recommendations, 1908-1909 (Box 15)
- Appointments and Salaries, Series 4
  - Salary rolls and letters of appointment, Apr 1901-May 1903 (Box 16)
  - Salary rolls and letters of appointment, May 1903-Nov 1905 (Box 16)
  - Salary rolls and letters of appointment, Mar 1906-Aug 1909 (Box 16)
  - Salary rolls and letters of appointment, Jan 1906-Dec 1908 (Box 16)
  - Salary rolls and letters of appointment, Aug 1909-Jun 1910 (Box 16)
  - Advisory Board Letters from Jordan concerning appointments, May 1904 -July 1906 (Box 16)
  - Salary Lists, Sep 1921-Aug 1924 (Box 16)
- Official Letterbooks; Official Letters from the President, Series 5
  - Feb 1902-Dec 1903 (Box 17)
  - Feb 1905-Jan 1906 (Box 17)
  - Jan 1906-Aug 1906 (Box 17)
  - Aug 1906-Mar 1907 (Box 17)
  - Jun 3, 1900-Nov 20, 1900 (Box 17a)
  - Nov 10, 1902-Dec 24, 1902 (Box 17a)
  - Dec 18, 1903-Mar 27, 1905 (Box 17a)
    [To the Board of Trustees and individual trustees, includes salary rolls and other business data]
  - Aug 1904-Sep 1904 (Box 17a)
  - Mar 3, 1904-Apr 12, 1904 (Box 17b)
  - Nov 1, 1904-Dec 14, 1904 (Box 17b)
  - Jul 24, 1906-Sep 17, 1906 (Box 17b)
  - Jan 13, 1906-Feb 10, 1908 (Box 17b)
  - Mar 14, 1907-Dec 12, 1907 (Box 17c)
  - Aug 5, 1907-Sep 25, 1907 (Box 17c)
  - Sep 25, 1907-Nov 14, 1907 (Box 17c)
  - Feb 10, 1908-Mar 11, 1908 (Box 17c)
  - Dec 11, 1908-Nov 18, 1909 (Box 17d)
  - May 25, 1909-Aug 24, 1909 (Box 17d)
  - June 1910 (Box 17d)
  - Jan 1908-Dec 1908 (Box 18)
  - Nov 1909-Jun 1910 (Box 18)
- Miscellaneous Documents, Series 6
  - Letters from the Academic Secretary concerning actions of the Board of Trustees, Apr 1902-Jul 1913 (Box 18)
  - Notarial record of George A. Clark, Notary Public, 1908-1911 (Box 18)
  - Study on why Eastern students come to Stanford, 1902 (Box 18)
- Contracts and Agreements, Series 7
  - Agreements between Jane Stanford and David Starr Jordan, John Stillman, and Charles Marx re rental of Encina and Roble Halls, 1893-94, 1894-95; 2 TDs (Box 19, Folder 1)
  - Contract between Jane Stanford and Jordan re University budget, 1894-95; TD (Box 19, Folder 1)
  - Agreements between Jane Stanford and David Starr Jordan re payment of faculty salaries and student registration fees, 1894-1898; 4 TDs (Box 19, Folder 2)
  - Agreements between Jane Stanford and David Starr Jordan re payment of faculty salaries and student registration fees, 1898-1902; 5 TDs (Box 19, Folder 3)
  - Grounds lease of university [printed form with typed draft revisions], undated (Box 19, Folder 4)
  - "Regarding Ground Lease" [explanantion of terms of leases], undated (Box 19, Folder 4)
  - Professors salary roll, typed list, 1899-1900 (Box 19, Folder 4)
  - Agreement between Jane Stanford and David Starr Jordan re monthly allotment for university expenses, Oct 31, 1896 (Box 19, Folder 4)
- Report of Committee Actions (Standing Committees of the Faculty)
  - Committees included: Student Affairs, Graduate Study, Ways and Means, Admission, Registration, Scholarship, Athletics, Public Exercises, Public Health, Hopkins Laboratory, Advisory Board, Medical Curriculum, 1898-1906 (Box 20)
  - Committees included: Student Affairs, Graduate Study, Ways and Means, Admission, Registration, Scholarship, Athletics, Public Exercises, Public Health, Hopkins Laboratory, Advisory Board, Medical Curriculum, 1905-1910